2020 Express for Rhythm is an up-and-coming lounge here in San Diego, California, that
fuses performing arts with social justice. It is a place where the two purposely collide
with the intention of using performing arts from intellectual books, from creativity,
from artistry, from painting, singing, performing, dancing, whatever the case may be, but using
it to send a political message, using it to build a community, using it to build humanity,
and using art as a driving force for intellectual conversation, for intellectual elevation.
And so I'm really excited to have my first event with 320 be partnered with the incredible
Amanda Seals. Thank you all for coming out, and not because that's what we're supposed
to do, and it sounds nice on stage, but I want to thank you for coming out because the
world is not easy. The world is very hard on us, and many of us are suffering in ways that
we may not feel comfortable or safe enough to explain. Many of us are impacted by the
atrocious attacks of this administration. Many of us are impacted by the influx of this economy.
San Diego is one of the most expensive cities to live in, and somehow, every month, we seem
to keep pushing through and managing. Some of us are now facing food insecurity, and for
those of you that were willing and able to bring food tonight, thank you.
It was really important for me to thank you for your time, because now more than ever,
our resources are slim. That means our gas. That means our physical energy. That means our
physical time. And so I deeply, from the bottom of everything I have, want to thank you for taking
time to come out to an event with an organization you never heard of, but you did hear of Amanda,
and continuing to support her work, continuing to support her as an artist, as an activist,
as an intellectual, and more important, making sure that we are putting our money into the economies
that we want to see grow. People like Amanda who speak the truth. People like 320 that are here
to make sure we have safe spaces for liberation. And we also want to thank this beautiful place
and facility in which we're partnering in, the Chrysalis Monarch Performing Arts. This building
in particular is a nonprofit that is connected to an incredible school that focuses on a program,
an educational program, specifically for unhoused youth. Not only does it take care of the unhoused
youth, it provides wraparound services for their families. So much so that those that are unsheltered
and unhoused prior to school can come on campus to use showers, can use the food bank to ensure
that they have food and meals, can ensure that they have clothing, any child care needs, health care needs,
mental health needs. It is a wraparound service school, ensuring that our unsheltered community
still has a foundation to keep going, and the start that they need to live the life
that they are destined to live, without the implications of this world, without the lack
of humanity. It is a place centered in love. It is a place centered in community. And so we
are honored to be in this space because the proceeds in which they raise for these venue space goes
right back into the work that they do. So give it up for Monarchs.
For one person, and one person only. And so I want to introduce her properly, and we are
going to engage in an incredible intellectual edutainment experience. We would like you to
have your phones turned off, have them on silence, make sure that we don't have interruptions.
Okay, here we go. Amanda Seals is an artistic intellectual whose work embodies what she calls
artivism. Activism through art. Through her signature brand, edutainment, she uses humor, history, and truth
to both enlighten and empower. Holding a master's degree in African American Studies from Columbia University,
Amanda seamlessly merges scholarship and artistry, intellect, and creativity to spark necessary
conversations about culture, justice, and identity. As a visionary force behind Smart, Funny, and Black
Productions, she has built an ecosystem of original work that speaks directly to the heart and soul
of the Black experience. Her latest creation, What Would the Ancestors Say?, began as a one-woman show,
blending humor, history, storytelling to challenge us to reflect on two essential questions. What would
our ancestors say about our world we live in now? And what kind of ancestors will be for the future?
Now, reimagined as a self-published written piece, it extends her mission to even further offering educators,
curators, communities, a timeless tool for truth-telling and learning about liberation. So please join me
in welcoming the brilliant, the spirited, the phenomenal, the liberator, Amanda Seals.
I'm bringing deep hands. Um, welcome, uh, please give it up one more again for Risa and all of you who put this together.
We had Risa two weeks ago like, hey, y'all, you trying to come to San Diego?
You think you could cook something up? And she was like, say less. Watch me work.
And so here we are. And we are talking about What Would the Ancestors Say?
What Would the Ancestors Say? Began as a one-woman show. And then I realized I needed to write it.
I needed to put it in text form. And we'll get to that later. But I want to introduce you to some
voices that are found here in the pages and, uh, help them help us go on a little ride this evening.
You down?
Are you down?
Which one is bad? And they put the black doll and the white doll.
I don't want to say that I'm the ugly one and the bad one, but I understand.
Because they don't know yet that liking me means you're going to grow up to be a bad ass
motherfucker. Because that means you already love yourself.
Now, imagination. Did you know imagination?
Like y'all sleep right in front of your face.
But we not listening to them because we can go whenever we want.
I'm going to take y'all on a little ride. Y'all want to go through the portal with me?
Y'all sound forward of What Would the Ancestors Say.
I believe wholeheartedly that our resistance efforts to achieve collective liberation
have been greatly weakened by the initial sin of the forced disconnection of our ancestors from their
greatest sources of strength. Their land, their gods, and each other. Thus, I theorize that we must reclaim
our connection to land, spirit, and empathy in order to break through the barriers that have been built in
the present. You see, there is immediate work that we have to do for our necessities of life.
We have to make sure people are fed. We have to make sure people have rules over their heads.
We have to make sure people are clothed and have health care. We also have to meet their minds.
And everyone in here is a part of a project that has been going on longer than most of us have been alive.
And that project has been a war for our minds. For our black people in here, it is because we never got
to own the land that we were forced to toil. We were, many of us, stolen and placed upon a land
that was foreign with people that were foreign with people that were foreign and made to create an entirely
new existence. We are in a unique form of indigeneity. And so I say that our bodies are the soil.
Our bodies have been that which is colonized. In the same way that we have seen the colonizer colonize the
land of the indigenous people all over this world. They poison the land. They steal the land.
They commodify. They take the land and turn it into something and say, come on on this land, look.
They ruin it. They ruin it. They deceive. And so we find ourselves at a time where some of us
have been able to successfully decolonize and rewire. We've somehow managed to move from out
out of the war that we are in and into fighting back. But not enough of us have. And I am doing
not the work of feeding the people, though I help. I'm not doing the work of housing the people, though I help.
I'm not doing the work of clothing and providing medical health care for the people, though I help.
My work is for the minds of the people. Because all of those things are never going to get fixed.
Our society will never shift if our minds don't. Because we need to get them back.
Now, we have to understand that if there's barriers, right, what are...
So I'm going to say a word, and then I want somebody to raise their hand, and I'll call on you,
and I want you to tell me what you consider the definition of that word to be. All right?
All right? Pics. Nobody can define politics. Race is a color, not an ethnicity, but yeah.
A game. A game. Politics is a game. Correct.
Technically, it's the process of governance, right? And we have become so forgiving of that process.
Have y'all noticed? Accepting that it's dirty. It's a dirty game. They're going to have to lie.
They can't do nothing. We are the ones who allow for politics to be a game of creating something for us.
That is a barrier that then moves forward into the next word. Capitalism.
You knew that was coming. Can anyone define capitalism? Yes, love?
That is an example. Yes? Same. Exactly.
You see, capitalism is, on a basic level, like the cutesy version, is corporatizing governance.
Right? That's the bite size. That's the travel size.
You know that rack of little lotions when we used to go to Target? Way back in last year.
I say way back in last year, because last year was way back when.
We done lived 60, we done lived 50, 11 lives. I used to stand up last year, and I was like,
person last year? Oh my God. Now I have locks and a nose ring. I'm very deep.
If I come out with a septum, y'all going to be like, she's a lesbian.
At least by. Governance. It is a system of government that makes the needs and necessities of living
private affairs upon which people can profit from. We are experiencing hyper-capitalism right now.
In such an extreme, bonkers, HBO movie way, right?
These niggas were having a party, let me just say, these niggas were having a party the other day,
with like feathers and shit. While the government, the gunman, is shut down, ain't snapping.
They're doing this because they want to shame people on snap. If y'all don't shut up, that is,
it's so much deeper, and this is why I need us to get out from under. Because we need to be able to
see the barriers to break them down. They don't want to shame people on snap. That assumes that they
even see you as people. That assumes that they even consider feelings. The only use of feelings
for the barriers that we are discussing is in the use of harming for manipulation.
I believe that the reason they are stopping snap is because they want folks on snap to snap.
And so that that's when many of us as community have to say, well, how do we prevent this?
How do we provide for what the corporatizing of governance is denying? And they're denying food
and essential necessities for the people while providing for the next one here. Can anyone define
for me oligarchy? Yes? Yes. And I would add to that by very few. It's an extremely wealthy tycoon board of greed.
And what's fascinating is that they are seen as the elite when they are really just the elite thieves
of the time. They make the Paris heist look messy. Okay? These folks are stealing from not just people.
They are stealing from the planet. Elon Musk figured out how to steal from the sky.
We are witnessing the oligarchy. However, I want you all to know that it has always been here in the United States.
The United States has always been bailed out by rich mofos. So when people say my country, I'm like,
you don't know shit about your country. So there's this, this talk about American values. I really think
American values is hot dogs and polo shorts with matching polo shirts. I think some people think
American values is, you know, golf and camping. I'm like, no, that's just shit white people were doing
and they wouldn't let black people do it with them. And then when we started doing it, we was on another
level with it. Now I don't like Oprah and Gayle, but had you seen them camp? Them chicks brought
out lobster tails at the campsite. So we've got politics, we've got capitalism, and we've got an
oligarchy. So if the energy is not going to protecting us, then what is it going to protect?
Them. And that is what empire is.
So when I stand here and I say we have to decolonize and rewire our minds in order to
fight it, we have to understand what is preventing us from decolonizing. What is preventing us from
rewiring? Because baby, we've been in a war this whole time that many of us didn't know we were in.
And they told you it was a conspiracy theory. But we have been the subject of a colonizing of our
our minds to not resist. They call it psyops, which sounds real like
I like that you understood from just the point. Real like born identity, right?
Sound real like black water rocks, maybe.
It's just short for psychological operation. Now some of y'all have been the subject of,
and are actually very proficient at performing psyops on your partners.
Your children. Any of us who have pets know that we have had to do psyops
because they act like they don't ever get fed. You're like, I don't understand. I fed you.
Psyops has been a key proponent to its power, to holding on to the roots that it stuck in the ground
post-World War II. Psyops uses propaganda and psychological methods to influence the emotions,
motives, and behavior of target audiences. I'm going to read you some definitions,
and then I'm going to read you the sentence that the Oxford Dictionary put with the word,
with the word, okay? Propaganda. Information, especially of a misleading nature,
literature, used to promote a particular cause or point of view. You know what the second definition
of propaganda is? A committee of the Roman Catholic Church, responsible for foreign missions,
founded in 1622 by Pope Gregory XV. I don't know about y'all, but if my clique is called propaganda,
I don't think I'm in the right. Misinformation, false or misleading information. The example sentence
provided, we urge them to disregard the misinformation circulating on social media.
Disinformation. False information that is intended to manipulate. Example sentence. The entire Western
intelligence system had been systematically manipulated with clever disinformation. Niggas know.
The days in which we find ourselves being colonized on a daily basis.
And it is our ancestral knowledge that we have to look into and we have to reconnect to, to decolonize and rewire.
Anything that the United States has told you was not good or bad, you should be making it your business to learn.
The United States told you Russia ain't shit. Now, baby, I need to learn about Russia on my own time.
The United States told you North Korea was the worst. Well, I guess I'm going to have to.
The United States has told you the Constitution is just too, it's too difficult to understand.
So you got to go get a law degree in order to do it. You know what? Let me read this, bitch.
Let me read this Constitution. The United States is now telling you that black history does not exist.
That all black history is, is shame for white people. Anything the United States tells you is not good, you need to learn about.
The United States tells you that socialism is terrible. That communism is terrible.
You have to learn for yourself. The United States is a country that has never cared about you.
So you should not be taking its advice on what you need to know.
Expand beyond limitations that were provided for us.
The same folks that made those limitations rendered your ancestral learning, your ancestral wisdom, savage, uncivilized, and disconnected you from it in the name of elevating you to their level.
But their level was not an elevation. It was a disconnect because you don't need to be elevated when the ground that feeds you and that is a source for you is beneath you.
You need to get grounded in that.
And so when we talk about the ways in which our resistance movements have been unable to move forward, have been unable to sustain, we have to think about the ways in which we, particularly in the United States, have been disconnected from systems of wisdom that the indigenous and ancestral folks who came before us had established and were living within.
And that we now look at it as like whimsy or witchery shit.
The astrology girlies will tell you.
They're right up here.
Girl, you know there's a transit tonight.
I don't know if I'm going to go out.
A picture of a leather of the sky from the world.
I tried.
A hundred something.
This is before access to telescopes.
It's actually before 1800.
This is before the ability to commune with lenses, et cetera.
We know the people of Africa have been identified celestial wonder long before the Greeks was like, oh, look at this.
Timbuktu existed long before these people was even knowing how to wash.
I mean, it's still an issue.
But it's like, anyways, because they're right there.
The labor, the point.
So that means you're not herbology.
The knowledge of plants.
Is that a baby?
It's a dog.
What?
Bring the dog up, please.
There's two dogs?
Bring the dogs up, please.
Your lives already be coming.
You feel me?
I know that there are so many of us who are literally just now waking up and we're over 40.
We halfway over this tip.
I don't know.
Jill Stein read my pot the other day and she told me I'm going to live really long.
And I was like, ugh.
Really?
She was like, mm-hmm.
I said, we'll see if we see a Green Party president in my lifetime.
She, he said, mm-hmm.
Want to understand how to decolonize?
You got to understand the effort that was put in place to colonize, right?
The phases.
1947 to 1948 was a wild time, y'all.
Wild time.
Several things happened at one time.
You got the partition of India and Pakistan.
You got the supplanting of apartheid in South Africa.
The system of governance that says that these people deserve these rights and those people deserve those rights.
You have the 38th parallel separating Korea into North Korea and South Korea.
You have the Nakba in Palestine.
And you have the founding of the CIA.
Isn't it funny how certain things, it just feels like they were always there?
You know they didn't create credit scores until like 1988.
And you know they only created it for what?
Everything is pretty much racism.
You know why the characters in Disney wear white gloves?
Say it with me.
Yeah, because they thought that black hands would look icky.
You know why there's the SAT and the ACT?
Yes.
I'm not going to do a chorus with y'all.
Because y'all can't even say racism at the same time.
In the book, I talk about the fact that we have never been wanted here in the United States as black people.
As free black people.
Every time a law has been passed or some type of act has been put in place for the supposed assistance or support of black people,
it has always been begrudgingly.
I call them the here-nigga-damn laws.
Because they're always giving like,
here-nigga-damn-ah!
Like when somebody owe you money and you're like,
no really, can't you just give me my money?
And they're like,
it's like when you order food from a Jamaican restaurant.
And by the way, if they don't treat you like that, it's probably not going to be good.
The here-nigga-damn laws include the Civil Rights Act of 1964,
the Bullying Rights Act of 1965,
the Housing Rights Act of 1968, 69.
And all of these acts get presented to us in the now
as if these were like laws that LBJ and that government did for black people.
This was for the blind you.
The amount of death and destruction that was happening prior to
and then leading up in the early 60s was inconceivable.
About assassination after assassination after assassination.
You're talking about the bombing of children in churches?
You're talking about children being on,
doing a march because their parents are going to get fired if they march?
Happening in a short, concise amount of time
that in the present gets treated as this like long extended era.
It wasn't.
It was the end, the culmination of a fight that had been going on
since the day slavery ended.
And the day slavery ended didn't even end for everybody.
My name is Whitby.
How y'all doing?
What's up with you?
Oh, man, y'all like that.
Yeah, might have put me in the book
because there's a rumor
that we've been hearing about up in heaven.
I'm up in heaven.
Yeah, I'm in heaven.
Apparently, y'all think that we didn't know slavery ended.
And so on June 10th, we were surprised
that we were free.
But I got to tell you, that's actually not true at all.
Baby, we knew we were free.
That was the talk of the time.
Shit.
Man, when we heard about that Lincoln
about to bring that emancipate proclimate,
it's the fact that someone over here went, stupid.
Because you're correct.
Baby, we was on them mules.
We was on them pies.
We was on them houses.
We was in them fields.
Everybody was talking about it.
What you going to do, man?
What you going to do?
We was ready to pack up.
Y'all would.
And once it came down,
shh, I was the first one out of them.
Around them.
So I was also the first one they strung up.
Amen.
I'm going to tell you what I don't tell you in this book.
The reality is,
your life going to be whatever you accepted to be.
I was going to be free,
whether it was down here or up there.
Because at the end of the day,
I'm not accepting nothing that ain't for me.
They give somebody a rope.
Most people say,
well, I guess I got to do what I got to do with this rope.
Sheet.
I say, well, this rope.
This rope ain't long enough for me.
Give me a longer rope.
And people going to look at you.
Who the hell do you think you is asking for a longer rope?
I'm someone who know I deserve that.
I deserve whatever I need.
And can't nobody tell me what I don't deserve if I'm willing to do what I am willing to do for it.
That was the same rope they hung me with.
But you don't got to live like that.
We live like that for you.
So for you down here to still be accepting the short rope,
man, that's an insult to us.
The short rope is what they been giving y'all.
And they just keep dressing up different.
They keep twisting up different.
And maybe you think it's something new.
But I've been here.
And I can tell you, it's the same rope and rope.
So I'm asking you, what y'all going to do differently?
You think they ain't going to string you up?
We're just in a time loop, y'all.
We have different clothes.
We have technology.
We have all these other distractions.
But we're in an era of the human race
where we are allowing ourselves to consistently be co-opted
by the same people over and over and over again.
Ask yourself,
that is a North American Negro spiritual.
Because Deborah is from Canada.
She tried that love thing for the last time.
People specifically ask if we could sing at the book talk.
I say, you ain't saying none of the words.
So the first theme of deprogramming that you're going to find
in What Would the Ancestors Say
is about demanding what you deserve.
But you can't demand what you don't know.
So if you don't know where you came from
and you don't know where you are,
then you don't know what you need
and you don't know what you deserve.
If you don't know what you're about,
you don't know what your worth and your value is
and how can you know what you deserve.
And if you are relying on a system to tell you that
based on your job,
if you're relying on a system of patriarchy
to tell you that based on your partner,
if you're relying on a system of capitalism
to tell you that based on how you look,
then you're lost already.
Because the person who's telling you,
the people who are telling you,
the system that's telling you what you deserve
is already busy making a rope that's too short for you
because that is what they have decided you deserve.
And we say they and we are not talking about
some mystical, magical people in the sky.
We are talking about particular individuals
who have names who are running the world.
They're not mysteries.
They're not hidden in bunkers.
They have names like Gates
and Musk
and Rockefeller.
They're out here.
They have names like,
what's the Walmart name?
Walton?
Yeah, Walton.
Walton.
DeVos.
What was that back there?
Soros.
Sister in the front said,
I'm trying to shake it up.
Obama.
You know, we're keeping it up.
It's the aspiration.
That's what,
that's what I feel
those folks,
because they would never let Obama in the club.
But it's the aspiration.
It's the willingness
to do the things
that may get you there
or at least aligned.
And that's what being the president is.
So we have to
encourage ourselves
to expand
as our next
theme of deprogramming.
What's good, y'all?
Yo, it's your man's
MC Checkerhole.
What's good?
So,
boom.
I'm in this book.
I'm in this book, right?
Because,
yo,
I was that dude.
And then,
you know,
I read the joints
and like know my whole story.
But what I really want to do
when you expand
what that do for you
beyond you.
I used to just be a cat on the block.
You feel me?
And then I started doing this rep thing
and I was,
yo,
I ain't even gonna be modest.
I was bummed out inside.
MC Checkerhole,
World Tour,
and all that.
You feel me?
Brrra!
And,
and,
and it was wild
because I was seeing
the world.
I was seeing
in ways I had never
even imagined.
Like,
I saw
pyramids,
bro.
I saw you on your phone.
I saw
the Great Wall of China.
That shit is dumb,
Lord.
And I ain't gonna lie to you.
It just busts my shit
wide open.
If,
if this is out here
that we could see,
just imagine what we can't see.
Cause all I have
on the Great
Late
Tupac Amaro Shakur.
Come with me.
Hail Mary.
Come quick, see.
And we have here now.
Yo,
cause Pac was,
in,
in one hour
and you like,
yo,
that's a deep cat right there.
But I couldn't really understand
until I
chose to expand.
And once I decided
I needed to know more,
I decided
everybody around me
needed to know more.
So it was like
I was
a library.
So I,
to pay it forward.
So as I expanded,
everyone around me
got to expand.
And next thing I knew,
yo,
my mans and them,
they was looking at the world
different famo.
That's what they don't
want you to do.
They don't want you to think
beyond money,
clothes,
cars,
and clothes.
Cause they could get you that.
Them scraps.
Keep you happy.
Throw a little Gucci on there,
a little,
some nut on there.
But when you want the truth,
nah,
they don't want to get you that.
When you,
when you want what's yours,
like the cats in Africa
with the minerals.
Nah,
they don't want to get you that.
Cause they like this,
this earth ours.
But nah,
when you start to expand,
you understand you from the earth.
So how the earth yours,
if I'm from here too,
they call the folks illegal aliens,
B.
They call in the same folks
that we can trace
back to the indigenous peoples
of the land.
Illegal aliens.
You know what an alien is?
It's otherworldly.
It's an outsider.
It's that which don't belong.
And it wasn't until I got expanded
that I understood.
Shit,
if we the aliens,
then y'all the parasites.
M.C. Check-a-ho represents
in the text
the mindset of so many
who,
the trick,
who believe the trick of capitalism,
that materialism
is really the pursuit,
and that that's really all you need,
particularly for black folks,
to expand.
It's not about expanding
your intellect.
It's not about expanding your spirit.
It's about expanding your wealth.
But many would say
that it's never enough,
is it?
You know,
there's a dope video
where a Native American man
is being interviewed,
and I don't know his name,
and I don't know what tribe,
what nation he's from,
but he says,
you see,
the difference between me
and the white man,
the difference between Native folks
is that if you ask
a Native man,
do you want a $50,000 house?
He would say,
absolutely.
However,
if you ask him,
are you willing to work
nine to five
every day
for someone else,
and it does not do anything
for your community,
and you don't get to see
the nature
and the world
that you are of,
do you still want
the $50,000 house?
And he said,
the Native man will say,
no.
And then he will be
looked at as lazy.
And he said,
but that's not lazy.
That's knowing
that the wealth
is in all
that you already have,
not in what
they are saying
is valuable.
We need a third one now.
There was a cough over here,
and then she joined me.
Yeah.
That's a team.
Y'all are a team, right?
Team players.
So when we're looking
at methods of decolonizing,
and we look into this text,
this book
seeks to present them to you
through different methods
and means,
through characters
and dialogue,
through themes.
And Shekho
is like so many of us
who unwittingly
find ourselves
following a dream,
following a talent,
following a passion
that unfortunately
has already been
embroiled in capitalism.
I experienced that.
I never wanted
to be famous.
That was never
a goal of mine.
But I was really good
at acting.
And I'm a performer.
She said,
that's it.
So there was a path
that you take.
And so I took that path,
and that path
took me to L.A.,
and I found myself
in the throes
of the goals
of Los Angeles.
And the goals
of Los Angeles
seem harmless
at first.
You're just trying
to make it.
And the longer you're there,
the more you really
give up to make it.
They're doing the opposite
of expanding.
They're narrowing.
They're making themselves
as light as possible
to slip through
that crack
that capitalism allows
only a few
to get through.
And in order to do that,
you can't talk too loud.
You can't say too much.
You can't be too honest.
You can't look too black.
You can't act too black.
Shit,
that might even be more.
It's okay to look like
you get act white.
What does act white mean?
Well,
you know,
it's fascinating
because the same people
out here
that have an issue
of being called white
are completely
denying themselves
the opportunity
to be connected
to something deeper.
They don't want
to be Scottish.
to be Irish.
They don't want
to be English.
to be Scandinavian.
They don't want
to be things
that are actual culture
because those things
don't give them
the right to oppress.
So they would rather
actually excise themselves
from that
in order to have
access to the right
to oppress.
I realized
that I couldn't
remain in L.A.
because the goals
that were there
I would never
have any interest
in pursuing.
I had met my goal.
I painted
up my mom's house
and like any
former rapper
would do,
I bought a Benz
with red leather interior.
In order to decolonize,
one of the hardest
things that you
have to do
is cultivate
your courage.
A baby.
Courage.
Folks talk a lot
about courage
when they're trying
to talk to you
into taking them
to get free.
Everybody got courage
on the field.
If you didn't know
yet, I'm your
ancestor, Harriet Tubman.
I done taken
a lot of folks
down that road,
up that road,
down that river,
up that river.
I done did it.
I done seen it.
We done gone
through the woods.
We done crossed
over creeks.
We done heard
the dogs barking
and kept on going.
And them same people
who back at the ranch
were saying,
where we going?
Where we running,
Moses?
When they hear
them dogs,
they get the friends.
When I got there,
showed them
the little friend
I bring with me
to course correct, folks.
when the fear
get to taking them.
My pistol.
And I let them know,
turn around.
It's about to be
popping.
Somehow they get
everybody right back
on course.
You see,
when you're following
a star on the path
to freedom,
it's never easy.
And it always ends up
being under the darkness
of night.
The hardest time
to see.
Because you're moving
through a space
and time
that you ain't been
through before.
And it don't matter
who's leading you.
You're the one
who has to keep
the courage
to go there.
That is what it is
to decolonize
your body,
your mind.
It's a willingness
to go through
the path,
following the stars
that have been
set before you.
Trust it
that it's worth it
even when the
dogs start to bark.
You've got to find
somewhere
for your courage
to be stuck.
a reason
not to turn back.
It's so easy.
Because it would be
easier to just
go back to what
you know.
Even though you
didn't like it.
But I've seen
both sides.
And when I look down,
you ain't running back
what you ain't running
forward.
You're standing still.
And I'm sitting up there
wondering,
what can we do
to make you move?
Do I got to come
back down now?
You got to ask
yourself,
if Harriet
down in the tub
may come down
now,
will she shoot me?
See,
courage ain't
something we're
cultivating no more.
We see y'all
and we're cultivating
complacency.
We're cultivating
contentment.
Even though you
already know
what's happening
now,
ain't it?
In this process
has to be
courage.
And it only
will come
from you
understanding
who you
are
and who you
came from.
Because my
courage is in
you.
And that
ancestor that
you looked
to and
screamed to
earlier and
said,
greetings,
ancestor.
Their courage
is in you.
Silly to think
this,
but we are
the extension
of DNA
and cells
that have done
the same
work over
and over
again.
We are all
a miraculous
extension
of existence.
I don't even
know why we're
here.
But we are.
And we find
ourselves
constantly
challenged
to come up
with a purpose
for being here.
For some people
it might be as
basic as,
well,
I had these
kids.
So I got
the reason.
For me,
I understand
my purpose
is to use
this art
to remind
us of
what we
deserve,
to expand
us into
the capability
to possess
the courage
to go get
something better
for what's
ever coming
after us.
Because we
are not
a culmination.
we are
a continuance.
You know,
I really
learned this
in real
time
post-October
7th
from the
Palestinian
people.
The
Palestinian
people
through
the
live
and in
color
terror
that they
experience
signified
for me
that person
in the
United
States
have lost
the land,
the spirit,
the people.
They bombed
their mosques
and their faith
grew stronger.
They separated
them and said,
you can't come
back.
And so
across the
diaspora,
they took
it as
a necessity
to be just
as Palestinian
wherever they
are,
even if they
aren't in
Palestine.
And now
they've got
the rest of
us wearing
keffias.
And so
I said,
but Amanda,
they do
still have
their God
and they
have their
people,
but there
is a sense
in work
and I
would
disagree.
They're
working.
still here.
The effort
that has
been taken
is of
such extreme
measure
and they're
still
here.
They're
still
fighting.
And now
they're not
the only ones
fighting.
We're also
And now
we understand
that their
fight is our
fight and
it woke
us up to
the fact
that we
should have
been fighting
for ourselves
this whole
time as
well.
Because
theirs may
have been
a war
of bombs,
but they've
been bobbing
our minds
this whole
time.
And the
lies that
have been
told through
the PSYOPs
to disconnect
us from our
courage,
the lies that
have been
dispelled to
disconnect us
from our
people,
the lies that
have been
pushed forward
to disconnect
us from the
lands,
has disconnected
us from our
empathy,
our ability
to see
anybody but
ourselves.
And the
first step
to decolonizing
is understanding
that we are
all here
together.
And that is
basic.
The Panthers
understood this.
Their first
principle was
all power
to all
the people.
Know this.
We understand
this,
but we're
not living
it.
And ever
so often
we are
given these
inferences
of light
to see.
It is the
darkness of
the genocide
in Palestine.
It is the
darkness of
the genocide
in Sudan.
It is the
darkness of
the genocide
in Congo.
It is all
of these
that need
to be
alchemized
into light
to light
us away
through
and to
remind us
of what
we're about.
As a black
person in
America,
I am so
tired of
my blackness
being distilled
down to
simply just
bamboo
earrings,
what's the
fan dance,
boots on
the ground,
and flaming
hot Cheetos.
We are more
than just
culture.
We have to
establish
values.
But don't
get it
twisted.
their culture.
They're like,
Juneteenth,
what's that?
I actually
do believe,
even for
non-black
people,
my name
is Ashley
H.
So I
started
celebrating
Juneteenth
prior to
2020.
It was
not the
federal
government
that had
me
celebrating
Juneteenth.
I have
a co-worker
named
Renita,
and she
is just
a lovely,
I was
using the
term
African
American
she
refers
to
be
referred
to
as
black.
So she,
I just
want to let
you know
that.
She is a
lovely black
woman who
really did
an incredible
job of just
making it clear
to all of us
at the job
that she was
not the
one,
the two,
or the
three.
and I
became
fascinated
with just
how much
I didn't
know,
you know,
like I
just didn't
know,
and my
curiosity
was so
piqued,
and I
just really
appreciate
that she
was really
willing to
just lead
me to my
own devices
by stating
it is not
her
responsibility
to educate
me,
and when
I asked
if there
was a
book list,
she said,
ask your
local
librarian,
and that
encouraged
me.
That really
reminded me
of my
own
strength,
and that's
what black
women do.
They remind
you that
you are not
using your
own strength,
and so I'm
so appreciative
to Renita,
and so ever
since I do
celebrate Juneteenth
the way it is
properly celebrated,
there are gringo
guidelines to
Juneteenth,
that have been
very clearly
laid out,
and I adhere
to them
every year,
me and my
husband,
Brad,
and my
three kids,
Jayla,
Braylon,
and Kaylin,
and, you know,
we're a deep
family, we're
very deep,
we're very deep,
we're a deep
family, so we
take things
very seriously
because we're
very deep,
and on Juneteenth
we follow the
clear gringo
guidelines which
state that you
should not speak.
And it's very
clear,
and I understand
it,
that white people
should not speak
on Juneteenth
because it is
the silence that
allows us to see
our blind spots.
It's the stillness
that allows us
to reflect on that
which we are still
perpetuating,
on that privilege
that we are still
existing in.
And though I am
divesting from
whiteness daily,
daily, okay,
I am absolutely
not about that
life, as
Renita would
say.
I understand
the realities
of the situation
and that I
cannot label
myself a
non-practicing
white.
That is something
that has to be
bestowed upon me,
kind of like a
knight, you know?
Like you are a
non-practicing
white, you know,
like with a
sword, or I
don't know, like
a bottle of
Luster's pink oil
or like something
like that.
So, I just
wanted to tell
everybody here
that Juneteenth
is really
important in
terms not of
the federal
government, but
just in recognizing
that there is
black culture and
history that exists
in this nation,
that even though
it is difficult
for white people,
it is imperative
for us to know,
which is why I
make an altar
every Juneteenth.
Bernita made it
very clear to me
that white people
who don't make
altars will be
haunted.
And you know
what they say,
trust black
women.
And so,
we do.
And we also,
we cap off the
evening at
midnight when we
are able to
speak again with
the singing of
a new Negro
spiritual.
You know.
You don't,
you don't know
the name
Negro spirituals?
Oh my God.
Why do you not
know this?
Do you guys want
me to sing it?
Yes!
Will you guys
sing along?
Okay, so,
the way that we
do it in my
household is we
hold hands because
it's about
togetherness and
community, so
don't let me go
get Bernita.
I'll wait.
I was going to
ask, is it like
a religious thing
or something?
Kind of.
Can she hold
your elbow or
whatever?
Excuse me.
I don't know
what it's about
me to act in
such a crazy
way.
Is that you
do when you
do what you
do to me?
It's a feeling
I don't want you to stay
The voice of my ancestors
And it took getting kicked out of Hollywood
It took getting ostracized by black Hollywood
It took getting attempted to be discredited by the Democrats
It took being forced to be by myself
For me to realize that first of all I ain't like none of them niggas anyway
For me to get silent
And hear that there was a greater voice
That I needed to be connecting to
And so when you look in this book
And you see all the images of ancestors that I have drawn
On different phone devices
It's because we are still connected
And we can call on them at any time
And they're calling on us to remember
That our excellence is not attached to capitalism
Our excellence is not attached to status
Our excellence is not attached to our ability to do the same as our oppressor does to us
It ain't about buying land
It's about learning it
It ain't about just being informed
It's about being in touch
And it ain't just about sharing culture
It's about sharing values
So before we close
I want you to remember that ancestor who we saw earlier tonight
I want you to turn to the person next to you
And I want you to tell them who that person is
And why you think they showed up
Talk about yourselves
We're just passing through
While we're here
We are a part of a long history in journey
And in being a part of that I want to be a valuable part of that
I want to be a responsible part of that
I want to do whatever I can
To give us a chance
To come back
Because I know I've been here before
And I plan on being here again
And those ancestors who came before that y'all were all talking about
They are here right now in you
And so
When you ask yourself
What would the ancestors say
I want you to know that you know the answer
And if you don't feel like you have the answer
Then you know what you need to be calling on tonight
Thank you
Bless you
And may the force be with you